Our Leaders. Ourselves.
The Queen is a drama, history film directed by Stephen Frears.
The Queen is an intimate behind the scenes glimpse at the interaction between HM Elizabeth II and Prime Minister Tony Blair during their struggle, following the
death of Diana, to reach a compromise between what was a private tragedy for the Royal family and the public's demand for an overt display of mourning.
The Queen, played by Helen Mirren.
Tony Blair, played by Michael Sheen.
Prince Philip, played by James Cromwell.
Cherie Blair, played by Helen McCrory.
Prince Charles, played by Alex Jennings.
Robin Janvrin, played by Roger Allam.
The Queen is a 2006 docudrama film directed by Stephen
Frears and written by Peter Morgan.
The film depicts the death of Diana, Princess of Wales in 1997.
The royal family regards Diana's death as a private affair and thus not to be treated as an official royal death, in contrast with the views of Prime
Minister Tony Blair and Diana's ex-husband, Prince Charles, who favour the general public's desire for an official expression of grief.
Matters are further complicated by the media, royal protocol regarding
Diana's official status, and wider issues about republicanism.
The film's development coincided with a revival of favourable public sentiment in respect to the British
monarchy, a downturn in fortunes for Blair, and the inquest into Diana's death, Operation Paget.
Michael Sheen reprised his role as Blair from The Deal.
He would play Blair again in The Special Relationship.
The Queen garnered widespread critical and popular acclaim for Helen
Mirren playing the title role of Queen Elizabeth II.
Mirren was praised by the Queen herself and was
invited to dinner at Buckingham Palace.
However, Mirren declined to attend due to filming commitments in Hollywood.
The film explores themes of dying and death, great britain,
upper class, loss of loved one, sadness.
The tone is emotional.